Guide to the Lessons of the Sixties: A history of local Washington, DC activism for peace and justice from 1960-1975: Interviews, 2010-2019 MS2388
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
- Interview: White, Harold, 2015 March 19; MS2388
  (1932-2015) - Rabbi Harold White was a long-time activist for civil rights, social justice, peace and interfaith dialogue. Beginning in 1968, he was an active member of Jews for Urban Justice (JUJ), which began by challenging the Jewish community of the Washington area to confront discriminatory housing practices by Jewish landlords. He was an active contributor to the first Freedom Seder in 1968. He was the first rabbi hired full-time by a U.S. Catholic university, spending more than half a century at Georgetown University teaching and counseling and promoting interreligious understanding. He was one of the first in the Washington area to perform interfaith marriages.
  Biography provided by the donor
  Keywords provided by the donor for Harold White interview: Rabbi Harold White, Mike Tabor, Jews for Urban Justice, radical/revolutionary, Fabrengen, become a rabbi "to save the world", JUJ, rabbi in Ann Arbor 1962-1968, Ann Arbor city council, open housing, Chair, Ann Arbor/Washtenaw Conference on Religion and Race, Chair, Ann Arbor Conference on Religion and Peace, civil rights movement, peace movement, peace marches in Washington, Max Ticktin, Hillel, work with students, JUJ in Washington, little involvement by local rabbis in peace marches, grape boycott, Gidalia Cohen, Giant Food, Joe Danzansky, oshek -Talmudic principle, food substance used for oppression is trayfe, Jewish classes for JUJ, large Victorian house on Q St, prophetic idea of justice, Jeremiah, Talmudic ethics, just war, Jewish mysticism, Kabbala, Abraham Joshua Heschel, Mordechai Kaplan, Shabbat service, May Day 1970, Adin Steinsaltz, safe house for May Day, Guardian Federal Savings, usurious interest, Arthur Waskow, new left orientation, prophetic tradition, shift in JUJ, politics of Israel, Freedom Seder, Channing Phillips, First Black-Jewish seder, Balfour Brickner, personal liberation, Sharlene Kranz, Sharon Rose, Zionism – Jewish national liberation, Arno Renard, Paul Rutke, Eleanor Epstein, Bob & Bonnie Aptekar, Arnold Sternberg, Poor People's Campaign, Balfour Brickner, Eugene Lippman, Theodore Bikel, Rob Agus, transition from JUJ to Fabrengen, Isaac Frank, Georgetown University, Jewish Community Council, "Shmatas for the Shvartzes program", freedom to express his views, limits of pulpit rabbis to speak up, Reform Judaism – prophetic Judaism, Al Vorspan – Reform leader, 1968 riots, burning of Jewish businesses, People's Peace Treaty, Abraham Joshua Heschel, Studied life of Ho Chi Minh, We were backing wrong side, 1966 prison chaplain, Purple Gang, transition from JUJ to Fabrengen, Judaism as a civilization – a religion, a nation and a people, Jewish renewal, spy for Jewish Federation Board in classes, turned Jeremiah into member of Fatah, Jeremiah a radical, David Shneyer, free Georgetown high holiday services, Bet Mishpacha, tribalism vs acceptance, covenant religion, co-director of interfaith project at Georgetown, conducted interfaith marriages, married Ronnie Karpen and Michael Moffit, Marcus Raskin second marriages, Ari Fleischer marriage, Pearl Bailey funeral, Washington Hebrew Congregation, Adat Shalom, not enough passion today for causes, JUJ people filled with passion, redemptive power of collective memory, Jewish United for Justice, Bar Mitzvah at age 83.
- Interview: Wolfson, Alice, 2017 April 11; MS2388
  Alice Wolfson is a veteran political activist and a pioneer in the women's health movement. She belonged to DC Women's Liberation, and was a member of "The Daughters of Lilith" collective. Hers was one of the leading voices protesting the lack of female participation in the 1970 Pill Hearings, as well as the deliberate withholding of information regarding oral contraceptives' dangerous side effects. Alice was one of the founders of the National Women's Health Network (NWHN) and organized many other actions during the NWHN's early years, including a sit-in in the office of the Secretary of the Department of Health, Education and Welfare, and the first FDA Protest. Alice served on the NWHN board of directors for several years. She also co-founded the Committee to Defend Reproductive Rights, which fought for and won both California state regulations protecting women against sterilization abuse and court decisions guaranteeing MediCal coverage of abortion. Today, Alice is a lawyer fighting for the rights of disabled individuals who have been discriminated against by their insurance companies.
  Keywords provided by the donor for Alice Wolfson interview: Alice Wolfson, women's movement, 1969, group living, women's health movement, birth control pills, abortion issue, DC women's liberation, Daughters of Lilith, side effects of birth control pills, Congressional hearings on birth control pills, long term health effects of the pill, closed hearings on the pill, need for warning on the pill, first patient safety warning in package, abortion was not legal, Guttmacher Institute, pill was welcomed, dalkon shield, DES daughters, anti-imperialist women's collective, Budapest women's meeting, women's voice in the anti-Vietnam War movement, Women's Strike for Peace, Toronto conference with Vietnam women, gay-straight split, Magic Quilt in DC, meeting place for Magic Quilt, Witches, guerilla theater, 1970, Code Pink, AIDS activism, organized own pill hearings, St. Stephen's Church, living in communes, welfare rights, DC General, mortality rates in DC, Etta Horn, estrogen replacement therapy, rise of midwifery, Our Bodies Ourselves, National Organization for Women, Betty Friedan, reproductive health movement, Off Our Backs, women's movement around the country, Children's House in DC, Marxist-Leninist Study Groups.